♪In the face of turmoil♪
♪혼란에 직면해서♪
♪Your roots hold firmly♪
♪당신의 뿌리는 굳건히 자리잡고 있습니다♪
♪To this piece of land♪
♪이 땅으로♪
♪Chasing after the waves♪
♪파도를 쫓아♪
♪My leaves flutter across♪
♪나의 나뭇잎이 펄럭인다♪
♪The horizon♪
♪수평선♪
♪Gazing from afar♪
♪멀리서 바라보며♪
♪At the end of the world♪
♪세상의 끝에서♪
♪Is eternity♪
♪영원하다♪
♪When we meet and then part♪
♪만나고 헤어질 때♪
♪When we rely on each other and then drift apart♪
♪서로 의지 하다가 멀어질 때♪
♪I have never forgotten♪
♪잊어버린 적 없어♪
♪As the glinting of swords cut♪
♪검의 반짝임이 끊어지듯이♪
♪Through the mottled sky♪
♪얼룩덜룩한 하늘을 통해♪
♪The falling dreams♪
♪떨어지는 꿈들♪
♪Shatter in the wind♪
♪바람에 부서지네♪
♪As the wind breaks through the waves♪
♪바람이 파도를 가르듯♪
♪It watches thousands of sails cross♪
♪수천 개의 돛이 교차하는 모습을 지켜봅니다♪
♪The vast land and the boundless sea♪
♪광활한 대지와 끝없는 바다♪
♪Armor and red robes flying high♪
♪갑옷과 붉은 로브가 높이 날아오르네♪
♪In the face of bitterness, intense emotions, and joyful adventure♪
♪씁쓸함과 강렬한 감정, 그리고 즐거운 모험에 맞서 ♪
♪I only wish you to be by my side♪
♪당신이 내 곁에만 있기를 바랍니다♪
♪Making the most of what life offers♪
♪인생이 제공하는 것을 최대한 활용하기♪
♪Like towering trees with interconnected roots, I'll accompany you to the ends♪
♪뿌리가 얽힌 우뚝 솟은 나무처럼 끝까지 함께하겠습니다♪
♪Watching fireflies land on our shoulders♪
♪ 어깨에 앉는 반딧불이를 바라보며 ♪
♪No regrets, no doubts in this world♪
♪이 세상에는 후회도 의심도 없어♪
=Wonderland of Love=
=사랑의 원더랜드=
=Episode 11=
=에피소드 11=
Cui Li, why are you blocking me?
추이리야, 왜 나를 막고 있는 거지?
Collaborating with the enemy,
적과 협력하여,
collaborating with the Zhenxi Army.
Zhenxi 군대와 협력합니다.
Why?
왜?
Are you not going to confess?
고백 안 할 거야?
Do you have any evidence?
증거가 있나요?
This is a secret letter from Li Ni
이건 리니가 보낸 비밀편지예요
of the Zhenxi Army wrote to you.
Zhenxi 군대가 당신에게 편지를 썼습니다.
You gave the Zhenxi Army
당신은 Zhenxi 군대를주었습니다
every detail of the situation of the besieged Yingzhou.
포위된 잉저우(Yingzhou)의 상황에 대한 모든 세부사항 .
The letter is crystal clear.
편지는 맑아요.
How did you get your hands on this letter?
이 편지를 어떻게 손 에 넣었나요?
Why?
왜?
You're finally admitting it now.
이제 드디어 인정하는군요.
It's rock-solid evidence.
그것은 확실한 증거입니다.
If it weren't for you,
당신이 아니었다면,
we didn't have to
우리는 그럴 필요가 없었어요
hand over Luoyang City to the Zhenxi Army.
뤄양시를 진시군에 넘겨줍니다 .
Arrest her!
그녀를 체포하세요!
Stop it!
그만해요!
Shiqi, you're finally back.
Shiqi, 드디어 돌아왔네요.
Did anything happen?
무슨 일이라도 있었나요?
We received an urgent military report.
우리는 긴급 군사 보고를 받았습니다.
Li Jun and Li Lai and their troops
리준(Li Jun), 리라이(Li Lai)와 그들의 군대
are closing into Luoshui.
Luoshui에 가까워지고 있습니다.
It looks like
그것은 다음과 같습니다
Sun Jing has long withdrawn his men
Sun Jing은 오랫동안 부하들을 철수시켰습니다.
from besieging my brothers.
내 형제들을 포위해서.
Those two brothers of mine
내 그 두 형제
sure don't disappoint me.
물론 나를 실망시키지 마십시오.
What are you doing?
뭐하세요?
Lin, you're here just in time.
린, 시간 맞춰 오셨군요.
I've long suspected
나는 오랫동안 의심해왔다.
that Lieutenant He has been contacting Li Ni from the Zhenxi Army in secret.
그는 중위가 Zhenxi 군대의 Li Ni와 비밀리에 접촉하고 있다고 합니다.
It was she
그녀였어
who leaked many of our military secrets.
우리의 많은 군사기밀을 유출한 사람입니다.
This is the evidence.
이것이 증거입니다.
It was Lieutenant He
그 중위였어요
who leaked the news about Yingzhou being besieged.
Yingzhou가 포위되었다는 소식을 유출했습니다 .
It was the reason
이유였어
we had to surrender Luoyang City.
우리는 낙양시를 항복해야 했습니다.
If Lieutenant He doesn't die,
만약 중위가 죽지 않는다면,
how can we face the soldiers
군인들을 어떻게 상대할 수 있나요?
who have fought valiantly on the battlefield?
전쟁터에서 용감하게 싸운 사람은 누구입니까 ?
Lin,
린,
I know you have a soft heart.
나는 당신이 부드러운 마음을 가지고 있다는 것을 압니다.
So,
그래서,
let me handle this for you.
이 일은 제가 처리하겠습니다.
So, you don't have to worry.
그러니 걱정할 필요가 없습니다.
Guards!
근위 연대!
Stop it!
그만해요!
Cui Li,
추이 리,
Taozi wrote this letter.
Taozi는 이 편지를 썼습니다.
Young Master is aware of this matter as well.
영스승님 도 이 문제를 알고 계십니다.
Recently, Lieutenant He noticed unusual activity
최근 허 중위는 특이한 활동을 발견했다.
within the army.
군대 내에서.
After she reported this to me,
그녀가 나에게 이 사실을 보고한 후,
she deliberately wrote this letter as bait
그녀는 일부러 미끼로 이 편지를 썼다
to see
보다
who would fall for it.
누가 그것에 빠지겠습니까?
You set me up.
당신이 나를 설정했습니다.
The letter is in my camp.
편지는 내 캠프에 있습니다.
If you didn't send someone to steal it
그것을 훔치라고 사람을 보내지 않았다면
because of your malicious intent,
당신의 악의적인 의도 때문에
how would it have ended up in your hands?
그 일이 어떻게 당신의 손에 들어갔겠는가 ?
Lin, I...
린, 나...
I did this
나는 이걸했다
because she's behaving very suspiciously.
왜냐하면 그녀는 매우 의심스러운 행동을 하고 있기 때문입니다.
I only wanted to assist you.
나는 단지 당신을 돕고 싶었습니다.
You have to believe me.
당신은 나를 믿어야합니다.
I was only trying to...
난 그냥 그러려고 했는데...
Father trained
훈련받은 아버지
the Cui Army.
추이군.
Our soldiers are united
우리 병사들은 하나가 됐습니다.
and follow a strict military code.
그리고 엄격한 군사 규정을 따르세요.
We've never had any internal conflicts
우리는 내부 갈등을 겪은 적이 없습니다
or power struggles.
또는 권력투쟁.
Cui Li, since you arrived,
Cui Li, 당신이 도착한 이후로
you've repeatedly tried to frame your comrades!
당신은 계속해서 동료들을 모함하려고 했습니다!
Do you think
당신은 생각합니까?
I didn't notice
난 눈치채지 못했어
your little schemes and ideas?
당신의 작은 계획과 아이디어?
When one frames his comrade,
동료를 모함할 때,
what is the punishment according to the Cui Army's regulations?
최군 규정에 따른 처벌은 어떻게 되나요 ?
Those who frame comrades will be stripped of their military power
동료를 모함하는 자는 군사력을 박탈당한다
and receive thirty strokes.
그리고 30타를 받습니다.
Cui Li, your five thousand soldiers
추이리(Cui Li), 당신의 오천 군사
will be temporarily commanded by Shu.
일시적으로 슈의 지휘를 받게 됩니다.
Since this is your first offense,
이번이 첫 위반이기 때문에
we'll skip the rod punishment.
막대 처벌은 생략하겠습니다.
Lin...
린...
Go!
가다!
This time, we managed to take the opportunity to reclaim Cui Li's military power.
이번에 우리는 최리의 군사력을 탈환할 기회를 잡았습니다.
I believe
나는 믿는다
he can't stir up any trouble now.
그는 이제 어떤 문제도 일으킬 수 없습니다.
Young Master,
젊은 스승님,
are you all right?
괜찮으세요?
Did you catch a cold from staying outside too long?
밖에 오래 있다가 감기 걸리셨나요 ?
I'll have Taozi come
타오즈(Taozi)가 오도록 할게요
and check your pulse.
그리고 맥박을 확인해 보세요.
Ying,
잉,
where did you go
어디 갔어?
when you left the camp today?
오늘 캠프를 떠날 때요?
I went to see Li Ni.
나는 Li Ni를 만나러 갔다.
Li Ni is the commander of the Zhenxi Army!
Li Ni는 Zhenxi 군대의 사령관입니다 !
You shouldn't have gone and met him privately multiple times!
여러 번 가서 그 사람을 개인적으로 만나면 안 됐어요 !
I know
알아요
you don't want to hear me say this right now.
당신은 지금 내가 이런 말을 하는 것을 듣고 싶지 않을 것입니다 .
But
하지만
as you saw today,
오늘 보신 것처럼,
we set up a trap,
우리는 함정을 설치했고,
waiting to lure the snake out of its hole.
뱀을 구멍 밖으로 유인하려고 기다리고 있습니다.
You went out on your own
스스로 나가셨군요
and gave Cui Li a chance to intercept you.
그리고 Cui Li에게 당신을 가로막을 기회를 주었습니다 .
What if he had really attacked you?
만약 그가 정말로 당신을 공격했다면 어떨까요?
Don't worry, Young Master.
걱정하지 마세요, 영 마스터님.
A mere Cui Li
단순한 추이 리에게
can't do anything to me.
나에게 아무것도 할 수 없습니다.
Ying,
잉,
I know you're confident and prepared.
나는 당신이 자신감 있고 준비가 되어 있다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
But things are unpredictable in a fight.
하지만 싸움에서는 상황이 예측할 수 없습니다.
If you had gotten hurt for real,
만약 진짜로 상처를 받았다면,
how could I feel at ease?
내가 어떻게 마음이 편할 수 있겠어?
Young Master, here.
젊은 스승님, 여기요.
Have some tea.
차 좀 드세요.
Drink it.
마셔보세요.
Are you feeling better?
기분이 나아졌나요?
Ying,
잉,
do you know something?
뭔가 아는 거 있어?
You mean more to me
당신은 나에게 더 의미가 있습니다
than anything else.
무엇보다.
Even...
심지어...
Even more than myself.
나 자신보다 훨씬 더.
We grew up together.
우리는 함께 자랐습니다.
I've always regarded you as an older brother.
나는 항상 당신을 형으로 여겼습니다.
So, you're also important
그러니까 너도 중요해
to me.
나에게
Yes,
예,
we share a sibling-like bond.
우리는 형제 같은 유대감을 공유합니다.
Saying these
이런 말을 하면서
unexpectedly...
뜻밖에...
Unexpectedly makes us feel distant.
의외로 우리가 멀게 느껴지게 만듭니다.
The physician has instructed
의사가 지시한 것
that you need a quiet rest.
조용한 휴식이 필요하다는 것입니다.
So, I won't bother you anymore.
그러니 더 이상 당신을 괴롭히지 않겠습니다.
Get some rest.
좀 쉬.
All right.
괜찮은.
At the latest, tomorrow,
늦어도 내일,
Li Jun and Li Lai will lead their troops to arrive in Luoyang.
Li Jun과 Li Lai는 군대를 이끌고 낙양에 도착합니다.
Those two
그 둘
have always been jealous
항상 질투해왔어
of your military achievements.
당신의 군사적 업적.
They must have come
그 분들이 오셨나봐요
with ill intentions this time.
이번에는 나쁜 의도로.
Shiqi, make up a plan.
Shiqi, 계획을 세워보세요.
Since my brothers have come,
형들이 왔으니까.
we should leave
우리는 떠나야 해
and give up Luoyang City
낙양시를 포기하고
to them.
그들에게.
Give up Luoyang City to them?
낙양시를 그들에게 포기하시겠습니까?
We fought hard
우리는 열심히 싸웠다
to take Luoyang.
낙양을 데려가려고.
And we even gave up three cities
그리고 우리는 세 도시까지 포기했어요
in exchange for the withdrawal of the Cui Army from Luoyang.
낙양에서 추이군을 철수하는 대가로 .
Now, do we just hand it over to them?
이제 그 사람들에게 넘겨주기만 하면 되는 걸까요?
It's the same if my brothers are stationed
형들이 주둔해도 마찬가지야
in Luoyang City.
뤄양시에서.
Quick and decisive action is essential.
빠르고 결단력 있는 조치 가 필수적입니다.
We'll head to Tong Pass.
통령(Tong Pass)으로 향하겠습니다.
How can it be the same?
어떻게 똑같을 수 있나요?
(Tong Pass)
(통패스)
I get it now.
이제 이해가된다.
Tong Pass is strategically located with the Wei River to the north,
통관(Tong Pass)은 북쪽으로 위강(Wei River)과 접해 있는 전략적 위치에 있으며 ,
Mount Qinling to the south,
남쪽으로는 친링산(秦寧山),
Central Plains to the east, and Guanzhong plain to the west.
동쪽은 중앙평원, 서쪽은 관중평원이다.
Plus, it controls the post road between Xichang and Luoyang.
또한 Xichang과 Luoyang 사이의 우편 도로를 통제합니다 .
It's highly contested military ground.
치열한 군사적 경쟁이 벌어지고 있는 곳입니다.
Sun Jing won't expect us
Sun Jing은 우리를 기대하지 않을 것입니다
to abandon Luoyang.
낙양을 버리고.
This will catch him off guard.
이것은 그를 방심하게 만들 것입니다.
Once we occupy Tong Pass,
통고개를 점령하고 나면,
it's like holding Xichang at its throat.
그것은 Xichang을 목에 쥐고 있는 것과 같습니다.
Then, we'll be close
그럼 우리 친해지자
to capturing Xichang.
시창을 잡기 위해.
That would be the best.
그게 최선일 것입니다.
As long as we hold Tong Pass,
Tong Pass를 보유하고 있는 한,
those brothers of yours won't have anywhere to advance
네 형제들은 앞으로 나아갈 곳이 없을 거야
or to retreat even if they want to take any action.
또는 어떤 조치를 취하고 싶어도 후퇴합니다 .
Shiqi,
시치,
I thought
나는 생각했다
you would go soft
넌 부드러워질 텐데
on those two.
그 둘에.
It's good
좋다
to see you're not.
당신이 아닌 것을 확인하기 위해.
I'm just looking out for my two older brothers.
나는 단지 내 두 형을 찾고 있을 뿐입니다 .
They tend to be overly ambitious
그들은 지나치게 야심적인 경향이 있다
and easily get carried away.
그리고 쉽게 쫓겨납니다.
It's better to let them stay in Luoyang City.
낙양시에 머물게 하는 것이 더 좋습니다.
Lest they fall into any traps,
어떤 함정에 빠지지 않도록,
and I have to go through great trouble to rescue them.
그리고 나는 그들을 구출하기 위해 큰 어려움을 겪어야 합니다 .
Young Master.
젊은 스승님.
Young Master, you're awake.
젊은 스승님, 깨어나셨습니다.
Where's Lieutenant He?
그 중위는 어디 있지?
She stayed in her tent all night
그녀는 밤새도록 텐트에 머물렀다
and didn't go out.
그리고 나가지 않았습니다.
Young Master,
젊은 스승님,
the physician has checked on you.
의사가 당신을 확인했습니다.
He said you fainted twice.
두 번이나 기절했다고 하더군요.
You must worry less,
걱정을 덜 하셔야 합니다,
and focus on your recovery.
그리고 회복에 집중하세요.
I know you're worried about Lieutenant He.
당신이 중위를 걱정하고 있다는 걸 알아요.
But sooner or later,
그러나 조만간,
she'll know you're the nicest person to her in the world, Young Master.
그녀는 당신이 그녀에게 세상에서 가장 좋은 사람이라는 것을 알게 될 거예요 , 젊은 스승님.
She's so intelligent.
그녀는 정말 똑똑해요.
Of course, she could feel
물론 그녀도 느낄 수 있었을 것이다
how well I treated her.
내가 그녀를 얼마나 잘 대했는지.
Then, you should feel at ease even more.
그러면 더욱 마음이 편해질 것입니다.
Lieutenant He isn't an ungrateful person.
중위는 배은망덕한 사람이 아닙니다.
Yesterday, you went to her rescue despite being ill.
어제 당신은 아픈데도 불구하고 그녀를 구하러 갔습니다 .
Seeing that,
그걸 보고,
she'll definitely feel moved.
그녀는 확실히 감동을 느낄 것입니다.
But what I want from her
하지만 내가 그 사람에게 원하는 건
is never her gratitude
결코 그녀의 감사는 아니다
or repayment.
또는 상환.
Master, stop drinking.
선생님, 술 좀 그만 드세요.
You haven't slept all night.
당신은 밤새도록 잠을 자지 못했습니다.
It's harmful to your health.
그것은 당신의 건강에 해롭다.
Cui Lin, you cunning fox.
추이린, 이 교활한 여우야.
You teamed up with Lieutenant He to trick me
넌 날 속이기 위해 He 중위와 협력했지
and forced me to hand over my military authority!
나에게 군사권을 넘겨주라고 강요했어요 !
It seems
것 같다
they're already suspicious of me now.
그들은 지금 이미 나를 의심하고 있습니다.
It won't be easy to act
행동하기 쉽지 않을 것 같아요
in the future.
미래에.
Master, we just received a secret report.
선생님, 방금 비밀 보고를 받았습니다 .
The Zhenxi Army sent a letter to Lieutenant He again.
Zhenxi 군대는 He 중위에게 다시 편지를 보냈습니다.
Does Cui Lin know about this?
추이린도 이 사실을 알고 있나요?
The secret letter was delivered directly to Lieutenant He's tent.
비밀 편지는 허 중위의 텐트로 직접 전달되었습니다.
The main camp is unaware of it.
메인 캠프는 그것을 인식하지 못합니다.
So,
그래서,
should we send someone to investigate?
조사할 사람을 보내야 할까요?
After what happened yesterday,
어제 일어난 일 이후,
Lieutenant He may lower their guard.
중위는 그들의 경비를 낮출 수도 있습니다.
We may never know
우리는 결코 알지 못할 수도 있습니다
if we find something.
우리가 뭔가를 찾으면.
As long as Cui Lin is here,
추이린이 여기 있는 한,
it won't be easy
쉽지 않을 거야
to take action against Lieutenant He.
허 중위를 상대로 조치를 취하기 위해.
But if we can discover
하지만 우리가 발견할 수 있다면
any information,
어떠한 정보,
it would be to our advantage.
그것은 우리에게 유리할 것입니다.
So
그래서
order someone to investigate
누군가에게 조사를 명령하다
the content of the secret letter.
비밀편지의 내용.
Don't leave any trace.
흔적을 남기지 마십시오.
(During my spare time,)
(나의 여가시간에)
(I often admire personal artwork.)
(저는 종종 개인 작품에 감탄합니다.)
(I'm currently creating artwork diligently.)
(현재 열심히 작품을 만들고 있습니다 .)
(Is it possible for me to ask for a beautiful portrait of you,)
( 당신의 아름다운 초상화를 요청해도 될까요 ?)
(so I won't feel lonely?)
(그러면 외롭지 않을까요?)
Lieutenant He,
그 중위,
aren't you going to reply to the letter?
너 편지에 답장 안 할 거야?
Why are you rushing?
왜 서두르나요?
No, I'm not rushing.
아니요, 서두르지 않습니다.
The letter isn't for me.
그 편지는 나를 위한 것이 아닙니다.
Since you're not in a rush,
서두르지 않으시니까,
so I'll handle some official documents first.
그러니 먼저 공식적인 문서 몇 가지를 처리하겠습니다 .
You can go back and get some rest.
돌아가서 좀 쉬시면 됩니다.
You don't have to keep me company.
당신은 나와 친구가 될 필요가 없습니다.
I'm not in a hurry.
나는별로 급하지 않아.
But Xie Chang'er who delivered the letter
그런데 편지를 전달한 셰창어(Xie Chang'er)
is in a rush.
서두르고 있습니다.
It's such a hot day.
정말 더운 날이에요.
He probably has gone back already.
그 사람은 아마 이미 돌아갔을 거예요.
You don't know
당신은 모른다
how stubborn that person is.
그 사람이 얼마나 고집이 센지.
If you don't notify him that you're not replying to the letter,
그 편지에 답장을 하지 않는다는 사실을 그 사람에게 알리지 않으면 ,
he'll definitely still be waiting outside.
그 사람은 분명 아직도 밖에서 기다리고 있을 거예요.
Lieutenant He,
그 중위,
I'll go and inform him, then.
그럼 내가 가서 그 사람에게 알릴게요.
I'm going now.
나는 지금 간다.
I'm going for real.
난 진짜로 갈거야.
I...
나...
Wait.
기다리다.
Since you're in a rush,
바쁘시니까,
I'll just write one to reply to his letter.
그 사람 편지에 답장을 한 통만 쓰겠습니다 .
Lest our little Miss Taozi
우리의 어린 Miss Taozi가
made a trip for nothing.
헛되이 여행을 떠났다.
All right.
괜찮은.
I'll wait for you.
나는 당신을 기다릴 것이다.
Lieutenant He, the scout reported
스카우트 중위가보고했습니다.
that the Zhenxi Army had withdrawn from Luoyang.
Zhenxi 군대가 Luoyang에서 철수했습니다.
Lord Liang's eldest son, Lord Linzi, Li Jun,
양공의 장남 임자 공 이준
has led his troop into the city.
그의 군대를 도시로 이끌었습니다.
By tonight,
오늘 밤까지,
Lord Liang's second son, Lord Kuaiji, Li Lai,
양공의 둘째 아들 콰이지공 리라이(Li Lai)가
will also arrive with his troops.
그의 군대도 함께 도착할 것이다.
All right.
괜찮은.
I didn't expect
나는 기대하지 않았다
Imperial Grandson to be so accommodating
황실 손자가 너무 친절해요
to his two older brothers.
그의 두 형에게.
He agrees to whatever they want.
그는 그들이 원하는 것은 무엇이든 동의합니다.
But Lieutenant He,
그런데 그 중위는,
where will he go
그는 어디로 갈 것인가?
after leaving Luoyang?
뤄양을 떠난 후?
Did he mention it in his letter?
그가 편지에서 그것을 언급했나요?
Of course, he won't mention it in the letter.
물론 그는 편지에서 그것을 언급하지 않을 것입니다.
If he didn't mention it in the letter,
만약 그가 편지에서 그 사실을 언급하지 않았다면,
what do you all write about then?
그럼 다들 무엇에 관해 글을 쓰나요?
Only some trivial matters.
몇 가지 사소한 문제만 있습니다.
(Please draw it yourself.)
(직접 그려주세요.)
Hello, Miss Taozi.
안녕하세요, 타오즈 선생님.
A letter our Lieutenant to His Highness.
우리 중위가 전하께 보내는 편지입니다.
Thank you, Miss Taozi.
고마워요, 타오즈 선생님.
I'll get going, then.
그럼 이만 갈게요.
Are you leaving just like that?
그대로 떠나는 거야?
Is there anything else?
다른 것이 있나요?
What's this?
이건 뭐죠?
This is a special healing ointment I personally formulated.
제가 직접 개발한 특별한 치유 연고입니다 .
You can't buy it outside.
밖에서는 구매하실 수 없습니다.
I thought,
나는 생각했다.
with all your military activities,
모든 군사 활동과 함께
there might be
있을 수도 있다
some bumps and bruises.
약간의 융기와 타박상.
If you use this,
이것을 사용하면,
you'll recover quickly.
빨리 회복될 거예요.
Thank you, Miss Taozi.
고마워요, 타오즈 선생님.
You're a nice person.
당신은 좋은 사람이에요.
Stop talking nonsense.
말도 안되는 소리는 그만하세요.
I'll get going then.
그럼 바로 갈게요.
Thank you!
감사합니다!
What a fool.
정말 바보 로군.
(Last night, I stayed in the countryside.)
(어젯밤에 나는 시골에 머물렀다.)
(The moon was as clean as if it was washed.)
(달은 씻은 듯 깨끗했다.)
(I felt like I could pluck the stars from the sky.)
( 하늘의 별을 따버릴 수 있을 것 같은 느낌이 들었습니다 .)
(A few days ago, I visited Zhuque Lane in Dongdu)
(며칠전 동두 주크레인을 방문했습니다)
(and bought some dried fruits.)
(그리고 말린 과일도 샀어요.)
(They tasted delicious.)
(맛있었어요.)
(They broke like fine jade as I chewed them)
(씹다가 순옥처럼 부서 지더라구요)
(and enjoyed chewing them through the long night.)
(그리고 긴 밤 동안 그것을 씹는 것을 즐겼습니다.)
(I hope to share this experience with you.)
( 이 경험을 여러분과 공유하고 싶습니다 .)
♪A fated relationship♪
♪운명적인 인연♪
♪Yet, playing roles that shouldn't be♪
♪그래도 해서는 안 될 역할을 하고 있어요♪
(I found combining dried nuts with preserved fruits)
(말린 견과류 와 보존 과일을 결합한 것을 발견했습니다 )
(enhances the flavor.)
(맛이 좋아집니다.)
(People in the past enjoyed them separately.)
(과거 사람들 은 따로 즐겼습니다.)
(But trying them together now,)
(하지만 지금은 함께 시도해 보세요,)
(the taste is intriguing.)
(맛이 묘하네요.)
♪Cut off resentment and hatred♪
♪원한과 미움을 끊어라♪
♪This colorful array across the sky♪
♪하늘을 가로지르는 이 화려한 배열♪
♪Belongs only to you and me♪
♪당신과 나만의 것입니다♪
♪You're the dawn of anticipation, hearts aglow♪
♪당신은 기대의 여명입니다, 마음은 반짝입니다♪
♪You're the final answer, no regrets, no woes♪
♪당신이 최종 답입니다. 후회도 없고 비애도 없습니다♪
♪My unspoken words are depicted in scrolls♪
♪나의 무언의 말이 두루마리에 그려져 있습니다♪
♪One after another♪
♪계속해서♪
(The horse leaped over the stream this morning.)
( 오늘 아침 말이 개울 위로 뛰어올랐다 .)
(Upon smelling the fragrance)
(향기를 맡은 후)
(and coming across a wild cinnamon tree.)
(그리고 야생 계피나무를 만났습니다 .)
(With its hidden aroma drifting in the air,)
(숨겨진 향기가 공중에 떠돌면서)
(I enjoyed this sight myself with deep regret.)
(저도 이 광경을 보며 깊은 후회를 했습니다.)
(Then, I picked several flower buds)
(그런 다음 꽃봉오리 몇 개를 골랐습니다)
(to create a fragrant sachet,)
(향기로운 향낭을 만들기 위해)
(hoping we could enjoy it together another day.)
(다음 날에도 함께 즐길 수 있기를 바랍니다 .)
♪I'm willing to abandon this world for you♪
♪나는 당신을 위해 이 세상을 기꺼이 버리겠습니다 ♪
♪No regrets in this lifetime♪
♪이번생에는 후회하지 않아♪
Lieutenant He!
그 중위!
Lieutenant He, I've been looking for you.
중위님, 제가 계속 당신을 찾고 있었어요.
So here you are.
그럼 여기 있습니다.
What's the matter?
무슨 일이야?
Nothing.
아무것도 아님.
I just want to ask
그냥 물어보고 싶어
if you're replying to his letter today.
오늘 그의 편지에 답장을 했다면.
Are you worried that Xie Chang'er
Xie Chang'er가 걱정되시나요?
is in a rush again?
또 급해?
No.
아니요.
I made an appointment with him
나는 그 사람과 약속을 잡았다
that Luoyang would be our meeting point
낙양이 우리의 만남의 장소가 될 거라고
to exchange letters.
편지를 교환하기 위해.
Luoyang as the meeting point?
낙양을 만남의 장소로?
Was it your idea
네 생각이었어?
or Xie Chang'er's idea?
아니면 Xie Chang'er의 아이디어인가요?
Xie Chang'er said,
Xie Chang'er가 말했습니다.
it was Mister Shiqi who suggested
제안한 사람은 Shiqi 씨였습니다.
meeting in Luoyang
뤄양에서의 만남
to make it easier to find each other
서로 쉽게 찾을 수 있도록
while marching.
행진하는 동안.
Xie Chang'er is the one
Xie Chang'er가 바로 그 사람입니다.
who delivers messages between the two armies.
두 군대 사이에 메시지를 전달하는 사람 .
By keeping track of when he arrives
그가 언제 도착하는지 추적함으로써
and calculating
계산하고
the speed of the horses,
말의 속도,
it's quite easy to figure out
알아내는 것은 아주 쉽습니다
where the Zhenxi Army is currently heading.
현재 진시군이 향하고 있는 곳 .
What?
무엇?
Li Ni is so cunning.
Li Ni는 매우 교활합니다.
Lieutenant He, only you
중위님, 오직 당신뿐이에요
could guess
짐작할 수 있었다
all his intricate thoughts and intentions.
그의 모든 복잡한 생각 과 의도.
Does that mean
그게 무슨 뜻인가요?
I'm cunning too?
나도 교활한데?
No,
아니요,
yours is wisdom.
당신의 지혜입니다.
So are you going to reply to his letter?
그럼 그 사람 편지에 답장할 건가요?
I don't know yet.
나는 아직 모른다.
What do you mean you don't know?
모른다는 게 무슨 말이에요?
Are you going to reply to him?
그 사람한테 답장할 거야?
Well, I really don't know.
글쎄, 난 정말 모르겠어요.
Well, will you write it?
글쎄, 써줄래?
Come on, write it.
자, 써보세요.
Someone went inside your tent.
누군가 당신의 텐트 안으로 들어갔습니다.
Taozi, come.
Taozi, 어떻게.
Let's take a walk.
산책 가자.
Lieutenant He,
그 중위,
are we not going in to catch that spy red-handed?
우리는 그 스파이를 적발하러 들어가지 않을 건가요 ?
No matter.
문제 없어.
Communicating with Li Ni using letters
리니와 편지로 소통하기
was meant to lure out this spy.
이 스파이를 유인하기 위한 것이었습니다.
Since they fell for it and acted foolish again,
그것에 반해서 또 어리석은 행동을 했기 때문에
then let them be.
그렇다면 그대로 두십시오.
Master,
주인,
this is the letter Li Ni wrote to Lieutenant He.
이것은 Li Ni가 He 중위에게 쓴 편지입니다 .
I thought of a way
나는 방법을 생각했다
and copied it word by word.
그리고 그것을 한 단어씩 복사했습니다.
"I found combining dried nuts with preserved fruits
"말린 견과류 와 보존과일을 조합한 걸 발견했어요
enhances the flavor?
맛이 좋아진다?
But trying them together now..."
하지만 지금은 함께 시도해 보세요..."
What's this?
이건 뭐죠?
In my opinion,
내 생각에는,
Li Ni and Lieutenant He
Li Ni와 He 중위
are both shrewd individuals.
둘 다 영리한 개인이다.
This letter appears normal on the surface.
이 문자는 표면적으로는 정상적으로 보입니다.
But it contains secret codes
하지만 비밀 코드가 포함되어 있습니다
with hidden messages.
숨겨진 메시지와 함께
That's why Lieutenant He
그렇기 때문에 그 중위는
didn't hide the letter in some hidden place.
숨겨진 곳에 편지를 숨기지 않았습니다 .
She just left it out in the open
그녀는 그걸 그냥 야외에 내버려뒀어
without being afraid of it being seen.
보이는 것을 두려워하지 않고.
The phrase about combining dried nuts and preserved fruits together
말린 견과류 와 보존과일을 함께 섞는다는 문구
must be their secret code.
비밀 코드여야 합니다.
That makes sense.
말이 되네요.
How about we get someone
누군가를 구하는 게 어때?
to decipher this letter?
이 편지를 해독하려면?
Of course.
물론.
(Since our parting,)
(우리 이별 이후로)
(just a few days have passed, yet it feels like years.)
(며칠이 지났는데 도 몇 년이 지난 것 같은 느낌이 듭니다.)
(I have never felt like this before.)
(이런 느낌은 한 번도 느껴본 적이 없습니다.)
(How I miss you so.)
(당신이 얼마나 그리웠는지.)
(At sunset, I saw some plump common water frogs.)
(해질녘에 통통한 물개구리를 몇 마리 보았습니다 .)
(I caught a few of them and roasted them.)
(몇개 잡아서 구워먹었어요.)
(Too bad the fire was too intense,)
(불이 너무 강해서 아쉽네요.)
(and they got slightly burnt.)
(그리고 약간 화상을 입었어요.)
(Letters)
(편지)
Master!
주인!
After a lot of effort,
많은 노력 끝에,
we've finally figured out the secret behind the communication
드디어 통신의 비밀을 알아냈습니다
between Lieutenant He and Li Ni.
He 중위와 Li Ni 사이.
Go on.
계속해.
Upon leaving Laolan Pass, Li Ni, Imperial Grandson,
라오란관(Laolan Pass)을 떠나자 황손 리니(Li Ni)가
has always excelled in long-distance raids,
항상 장거리 공격에 탁월했고 ,
using deception and diversion to create chaos.
혼란을 일으키기 위해 속임수와 기분 전환을 사용합니다 .
This time,
이 시간,
he left Luoyang voluntarily.
그는 자발적으로 낙양을 떠났습니다.
I'm sure he's using the same tactic.
나는 그가 같은 전술을 사용하고 있다고 확신합니다.
You have a point.
당신은 요점이 있습니다.
Keep going.
계속하세요.
Master Cui, please take a look.
마스터 쿠이님, 한번 봐주세요.
This letter is the most recent letter that Lieutenant He received.
이 편지는 그가 받은 가장 최근의 편지입니다 .
The phrase "caught a few"
"몇 마리 잡았다"라는 문구
typically refers
일반적으로 다음을 가리킨다
to a target staying by the lakeside.
호숫가에 머물고 있는 목표물에게.
By breaking down the phrase,
문구를 분해해보면,
doesn't it suggest an encircling strategy?
포위 전략을 제안하지 않습니까 ?
Then who's the target by the lakeside?
그렇다면 호숫가의 타겟은 누구일까요?
Now, isn't it a coincidence
자, 우연이 아닌가?
that our army happened to have passed by a lake
우리 군대가 우연히 호수 옆을 지나갔다고
and is now located by the lakeside?
지금은 호숫가에 위치해 있나요?
If nothing goes wrong,
아무 일도 일어나지 않는다면,
at sunset today,
오늘 해질녘에,
the Zhenxi Army will likely send someone to join Lieutenant He,
Zhenxi 군대는 He 중위와 합류할 사람을 보낼 것 같습니다.
coordinating an ambush against our forces.
우리 군대에 대한 매복 공격을 조정하고 있습니다 .
Master,
주인,
why not inform the commander of this now?
지금 이 사실을 사령관에게 알리면 어떨까요 ?
Then, we could set an ambush.
그러면 매복 공격을 할 수 있겠네요.
If we successfully repel the Zhenxi Army,
진희군을 격퇴하는데 성공한다면 ,
it would be a significant achievement.
그것은 의미 있는 성과일 것이다.
Indeed.
물론.
You fools!
멍청이 들아!
Master, calm down.
선생님, 진정하세요.
Answer me.
대답 해.
Everyone knows that Li Ni is trying to breach Tong Pass.
Li Ni가 Tong Pass를 뚫으려고 한다는 것은 모두가 알고 있습니다.
How can he simultaneously launch an attack on us?
그는 어떻게 동시에 우리를 공격할 수 있습니까?
Uh...
음...
It has already passed sunset.
벌써 일몰이 지났습니다.
So, where is Li Ni?
그렇다면 Li Ni는 어디에 있습니까?
Answer me!
대답 해!
Master.
주인.
Oh, Master.
아, 선생님.
Useless bunch!
쓸모없는 무리!
- What a useless bunch! - Please, Master.
- 정말 쓸모없는 무리야! - 부탁해요, 선생님.
Get lost.
길을 잃다.
I said, get lost!
내가 말했잖아, 길을 잃으라고!
Yes.
예.
We'll take our leave.
우리는 떠나겠습니다.
Where did you get these?
이것들은 어디서 구했어요?
Cui Li has been ordering his men to monitor Lieutenant He.
Cui Li는 부하들에게 He 중위를 감시하라고 명령했습니다 .
These are the letters he copied secretly.
그가 몰래 복사한 편지들이다 .
I obtained these
나는 이것들을 얻었다
from Cui Li's tent.
Cui Li의 텐트에서.
But Lieutenant He knew
하지만 중위는 알고 있었어
about Cui Li's action.
Cui Li의 행동에 대해.
But she didn't pursue it.
그러나 그녀는 그것을 추구하지 않았습니다.
Master, calm down.
선생님, 진정하세요.
I just remembered
방금 생각났어
something important.
중요한 것.
Previously, Lieutenant He used a letter
이전에는 중위가 편지를 사용했습니다.
to set us up.
우리를 설정하기 위해.
This reminds me
이게 생각나네
of how coincident it was.
얼마나 일치했는지.
It happened
그런 일이 일어났어요
after you met Pei Yuan.
페이 위안을 만난 후.
Are you saying
당신은 말하고 있습니까?
that after I met with Pei Yuan,
페이 위안을 만난 후,
he disclosed the plan to Lieutenant He?
그는 중위에게 계획을 공개했습니다.?
The two collaborated to lure me in?
두 사람이 협력해서 나를 유혹했다고요?
But shouldn't we
하지만 우리는 그렇지 않습니까?
be on the same side
같은 편에 있다
when it comes to killing Cui Lin?
Cui Lin을 죽이는 것에 관해서는?
If you want His Highness's letter,
전하의 편지를 원하시면,
it depends on whether you can kill Cui Lin.
Cui Lin을 죽일 수 있는지 여부 에 따라 다릅니다 .
It appears Li Ni has a close relationship
리니와 인연이 깊은 것 같다
with Lieutenant He.
허 중위와 함께.
Otherwise,
그렇지 않으면,
why would he share
그 사람이 왜 공유하겠어요?
such classified information with her?
그 사람한테 그런 기밀 정보가?
I previously considered
나는 이전에 고려했다
using Li Ni's hand to eliminate Lieutenant He.
Li Ni의 손을 사용하여 He 중위를 제거합니다.
But now it seems
그런데 지금은 그런 것 같다
not only he won't assist us,
그 사람은 우리를 도와주지 않을 뿐만 아니라,
but he'll also be against me.
하지만 그 사람도 나한테 반대할 거야.
Master, be patient.
선생님, 조금만 참으세요.
Those defending Luoyang
낙양을 지키는 자들
are Li Ni's two older brothers,
리니의 두 형이고,
Li Jun and Li Lai.
리준과 리라이.
They have always been at odds with him.
그들은 항상 그와 불화를 겪었습니다.
Why don't we join forces with them?
우리도 그들과 힘을 합치는 게 어때요?
This way,
이 방법,
we can resolve our issue of having no military authority.
군사권이 없는 문제를 해결할 수 있습니다 .
Excellent idea.
훌륭한 아이디어입니다.
(Tong Pass is a formidable stronghold, easy to defend and difficult to attack.)
(통령은 방어하기 쉽고 공격하기 어려운 막강한 요새이다.)
(Li Ni led his army and they fought for six days.)
(리니가 그의 군대를 이끌고 6일 동안 싸웠다.)
(With Pei Yuan leading the charge,)
(Pei Yu가 책임을 맡고 있습니다.)
(they finally captured Tong Pass.)
(드디어 통령을 함락시켰다.)
Congratulations, Your Highness.
축하합니다, 전하.
After the Zhenxi Army recaptured Dongdu,
진희군이 동두를 탈환한 후,
they captured Tong Pass not long after that.
그로부터 얼마 지나지 않아 통령을 함락시켰다 .
Tong Pass?
통패스?
That means they're not far
그 말은 그들이 멀지 않다는 뜻이야
from Xichang anymore.
더 이상 Xichang에서.
Yes, Your Highness.
예, 전하.
They're getting close
가까워지고 있어
to Xichang.
시창에게.
Li Ni chose not to contend with his older brothers
리니는 형들과 다투지 않기로 결정했다
and directly abandoned Luoyang.
낙양을 직접 버렸습니다.
He launched a surprise attack on Tong Pass, which is 500 li away.
그는 500리 떨어진 통관을 기습 공격했다 .
A bad bamboo can sometimes yield good shoots.
나쁜 대나무는 때때로 좋은 싹을 낳을 수 있습니다.
Lord Liang
리앙 경
sure has a capable son.
확실히 유능한 아들이 있군요.
Well, never mind that.
글쎄요, 그건 신경쓰지 마세요.
Lord Liang's three sons
양공의 세 아들
are now close by.
지금은 가까이에 있습니다.
As their father,
그들의 아버지로서,
he has been held up in the capital for a long time.
그는 오랫동안 수도에 억류되어 있었습니다 .
It's time for him to write letters to his sons.
이제 그는 아들들에게 편지를 쓸 시간이다 .
Sit.
앉다.
Shiqi, how did the battle go?
Shiqi, 전투는 어떻게 진행됐나요?
The overall situation is settled.
전반적인 상황은 해결되었습니다.
Don't pursue a desperate foe.
절박한 적을 추적하지 마십시오.
What about you?
당신은 어때요?
Are you all right?
괜찮으세요?
These are just flesh injuries.
이것은 단지 육체의 상처일 뿐입니다.
Great.
엄청난.
After battling hard for so long,
오랫동안 열심히 싸운 끝에
we've finally taken Tong Pass.
드디어 통패스에 도착했습니다.
My father said
아버지가 말씀하셨어요
Tong Pass is known as the strongest stronghold.
통령은 가장 강력한 거점으로 알려져 있다.
Since the founding of the nation,
건국 이래,
no army has been able to capture it.
어떤 군대도 그것을 점령할 수 없었습니다.
In the future,
미래에,
the Zhenxi Army can leave its mark in the annals of imperial history.
Zhenxi 군대는 제국 역사의 연대기에 흔적을 남길 수 있습니다.
Now, the situation has shifted from attack to defense.
이제 상황은 공격에서 수비로 바뀌었다.
So after this,
그래서 이 후에,
you'll only have to worry
넌 걱정만 하면 될 거야
about how to defend Tong Pass.
통패스를 방어하는 방법에 대해.
Shiqi,
시치,
is there another Zhenxi Army in this world?
이 세상에 또 다른 Zhenxi 군대가 있습니까?
There's also no other Shiqi in this world.
이 세상에 는 다른 Shiqi도 없습니다 .
Then, the world doesn't have
그럼 세상에는 없어
another courageous Pei Yuan.
또 다른 용감한 페이 위안.
Don't flatter me.
나에게 아첨하지 마십시오.
But Shiqi,
하지만 시치,
I have a question.
질문이 있습니다.
You know it's impossible.
당신은 그것이 불가능하다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
Why did you write letters
편지는 왜 썼어요?
to Lord Kuaiji and Lord Linzi,
Kuaiji 경과 Linzi 경에게,
asking them to jointly encircle Xichang?
시창을 공동으로 포위하라고 요구하는가?
My two older brothers are as stubborn as mules
내 두 형은 노새처럼 고집이 세다.
from being spoiled by my father.
아버지한테 버릇없게 굴지 않게.
If you want to go west,
서쪽으로 가고 싶다면,
they will insist on going east.
그들은 동쪽으로 가겠다고 고집할 것이다.
I don't want them to act rashly and send troops
나는 그들이 경솔하게 행동하고 군대를 보내는 것을 원하지 않습니다
to cause trouble to fight over merits
장점을 놓고 다투다 문제를 일으키다
at a critical moment like this.
이런 중요한 순간에.
So of course, I have to write letters to them to join the encirclement.
그러니 당연히 포위에 합류하기 위해 그들에게 편지를 써야 합니다 .
When I do this,
내가 이것을 할 때,
they're less likely to listen to me,
그들은 내 말을 덜 듣습니다.
and naturally remain idle,
자연스럽게 유휴 상태를 유지하고,
without taking any action.
아무런 조치도 취하지 않고.
This is called reverse psychology.
이것을 역심리학이라고 합니다.
Saying one thing but doing the opposite.
한 가지 말을 하지만 그 반대를 하고 있습니다.
(Luoyang)
(뤄양)
(Recipient, Brother.)
(수신인, 형제님.)
(Lord Linzi, Li Jun)
(Linzi 경, Li Jun)
(Please lead the troops. I'll siege and recapture the capital.)
(군을 이끌어주세요. 제가 포위 하고 수도를 탈환하겠습니다.)
(Lord Kuaiji, Li Lai)
(콰이지 경, 리 라이)
Jun, what did he write in the letter?
준 씨, 그 사람이 편지에 뭐라고 썼어요?
Read it yourself.
직접 읽어보세요.
Li Ni has captured Tong Pass.
Li Ni가 Tong Pass를 점령했습니다.
He wants us
그는 우리를 원해요
to deploy troops to surround Xichang?
시창을 포위하기 위해 군대를 배치하려면?
Jun, what is he...
준, 그 사람 뭐야...
Li Ni dares
리니가 감히
to order us around
우리에게 명령을 내리려고
by relying on his achievement
그의 성취에 의지하여
in taking Tong Pass!
통패스를 받아보세요!
Jun, being ordered around is one thing.
쥰, 명령받는 것도 일이야.
But deploying troops to surround Xichang
그러나 시창을 포위하기 위해 군대를 배치
is a serious matter.
심각한 문제입니다.
I'm afraid he intends to use our troops
그 사람이 우리 군대를 이용하려고 하는 것 같아 두렵습니다.
to help him achieve his goals.
그가 목표를 달성하도록 돕기 위해.
I've long known
나는 오랫동안 알고 있었다
that Li Ni is treacherous.
Li Ni는 배신자입니다.
We can't
우리는 할 수 없습니다
let his plans succeed.
그의 계획이 성공하게 해주세요.
Jun,
준,
didn't Cui Li of the Cui Army
추이군의 추이리가 아니었느냐
send a messenger here a few days ago?
며칠 전에 여기로 메신저를 보냈나요?
You mean...
네 말 뜻은...
Jun,
준,
I think
제 생각에는
we can lend troops to Cui Li
추이리에게 군대를 빌려줄 수 있어요
because he's lending the troops to kill Cui Lin
왜냐하면 그는 추이린을 죽이기 위해 군대를 빌려주었기 때문입니다.
and put the blame on Li Ni.
그리고 Li Ni를 비난하십시오.
That way,
그런 식으로,
he'll become
그는 될 것이다
a sharp blade
날카로운 칼날
in your hands.
당신의 손에.
Young Master.
젊은 스승님.
You have returned.
당신은 돌아왔습니다.
It must be a rough journey.
힘든 여정이겠죠.
How is Father's health?
아버지의 건강은 어떻습니까?
Great General is doing well.
위대한 장군님은 잘 지내고 계십니다.
But when he heard Young Master Cui Li came here without permission
그런데 최리대사가 허락도 없이 이곳에 왔다는 소식을 듣고
and interfered with military affairs,
그리고 군사 문제에 간섭했다.
he was furious
그는 화가 났어요
and ordered me to bring the command badge to you.
명령 뱃지를 가져오라고 명령하셨습니다 .
This is great.
이것은 훌륭합니다.
With this command badge,
이 명령 배지를 사용하면
I can order Cui Li back to Yingzhou.
Cui Li에게 Yingzhou로 돌아가라고 명령할 수 있습니다.
Then I no longer have to worry about him causing trouble.
그러면 나는 더 이상 그 사람이 문제를 일으키는 것에 대해 걱정할 필요가 없습니다 .
I can't believe
나는 믿을 수 없다
Cui Lin resorted to all means to obtain Uncle's command badge
추이린은 삼촌의 지휘 휘장을 얻기 위해 온갖 수단을 동원했다
to order me to depart back to Yingzhou
나에게 잉저우로 돌아가라고 명령하다
and not to follow the main army.
그리고 주군을 따르지 마십시오.
Cui Lin, you jerk.
추이린, 이 멍청아.
Am I that dreadful to you
내가 너한테 그렇게 무서운 걸까?
that you try every means to transfer me away?
나를 다른 곳으로 옮기려고 온갖 수단을 다 동원한다고 ?
Master, calm down.
선생님, 진정하세요.
We have received a reply from Luoyang.
뤄양에서 답변을 받았습니다.
Why don't we read what it says?
뭐라고 쓰여 있는지 읽어 보는 게 어때요?
(Grant the title of Grand General Weiyang)
( 위양대장군 칭호 부여 )
Master, what does it say?
선생님, 뭐라고 쓰여 있나요?
Li Jun has agreed to send troops
이준이 군대 파병에 동의했다
to help me kill Cui Lin.
내가 추이린을 죽이는 것을 도와주려고.
Once I succeed,
일단 성공하고,
he'll appoint me as Great General Weiyang.
그는 나를 웨이양 대장군으로 임명할 것이다.
Congratulations, Master.
축하해요, 마스터.
Congratulations, Great General.
축하합니다, 위대한 장군님.
As long as Cui Lin is dead,
추이린이 죽은 한,
I will command
내가 명령할게
the Cui Army rightfully.
Cui 군대는 정당합니다.
At that time,
그때에,
we can blame Li Ni
우리는 Li Ni를 비난할 수 있다
for everything.
모두를위한.
Two birds with one stone.
하나의 돌에 두 마리의 새가 있습니다.
Absolutely flawless.
정말 완벽합니다.
No wonder it was so difficult to conquer this place.
이곳을 정복하는 것이 그토록 어려웠던 것은 당연합니다 .
Look at the city walls
성벽을 보세요
and the surrounding terrain.
그리고 주변 지형.
It's truly a fortress
그야말로 요새다
that's hard to breach.
그건 위반하기 어렵습니다.
When we tried to capture it, it was tough.
우리가 그것을 포착하려고 했을 때, 그것은 힘들었습니다.
But now that our roles have switched to defense,
하지만 이제 역할이 수비로 바뀌었으니,
these natural defenses
이러한 자연 방어
are indeed advantageous.
실제로 유리합니다.
It is, isn't it?
그렇죠, 그렇죠?
If Laolan Pass had half of this natural advantage,
라오란 고개가 이런 자연적 이점의 절반만 가지고 있었다면 ,
we wouldn't need
우리는 필요하지 않을 것입니다
so many troops to defend it.
그것을 방어할 군대가 너무 많습니다.
Is it another letter?
또 다른 편지인가요?
Mister Shiqi,
시치 씨,
you must be eagerly awaiting news.
당신은 간절히 소식을 기다리고 있을 것입니다.
(Tong Pass)
(통패스)
Report!
보고서!
An envoy from Xichang has arrived!
서창에서 사신이 도착했습니다!
Grand Governor sent me to convey his order.
총독은 자신의 명령을 전달하기 위해 나를 보냈습니다.
The Zhenxi Army must withdraw from Tong Pass within three days.
진희군은 3일 이내에 통관에서 철수해야 한다 .
Outrageous!
터무니없다!
Did Sun Jing send you here to die?
Sun Jing이 당신을 여기로 죽게 보냈습니까?
General Pei Yuan.
페이 위안 장군.
Since I dared to come,
용기내서 왔으니까
I'm not afraid of losing my life.
나는 내 목숨을 잃는 것을 두려워하지 않습니다.
Also, there's a letter from Lord Liang
그리고 양경(梁君)의 편지도 있다
for you.
당신을 위한.
What if I insist on not withdrawing the troops?
군대를 철수하지 않겠다고 고집하면 어떻게 되나요 ?
If you don't withdraw,
철회하지 않으면,
then three days from now at noon,
그럼 지금부터 3일 정오에
Your Highness should prepare mourning attire
전하께서는 상복을 준비하셔야 합니다
to mourn Lord Liang.
Liang 경을 애도합니다.
I suppose my father
아버지인 것 같아요
must have written three letters.
세 글자를 썼나 봐요.
The other two have already been sent to Luoyang
나머지 두 개는 이미 낙양으로 보내졌습니다
for my two brothers, right?
내 두 형제를 위해서죠, 그렇죠?
Yes.
예.
I wonder,
궁금해요,
compared to Your Highness and your brothers,
폐하 와 형제들 에 비하면
which one of you is more filial?
너희 중 누가 더 효도적이니?
Lieutenant He,
그 중위,
you still haven't finished these dried nuts?
아직도 이 말린 견과류를 다 먹지 않았나요 ?
These were quite popular in Dongdu at that time,
당시 동두에서는 꽤 인기가 많았는데 ,
and people said they were delicious.
사람들이 맛있다고 하더군요.
Many people rushed to buy them.
많은 사람들이 서둘러 구매했습니다.
You're good at remembering all these details.
당신은 이러한 모든 세부 사항을 기억하는 데 능숙합니다 .
Originally,
원래,
everyone just ate dried nuts and kernels.
모두가 말린 견과류 와 커널을 먹었습니다.
But you prefer
하지만 당신은 선호
eating them with preserved fruits.
보존 과일과 함께 먹습니다.
How could I not remember something like that?
내가 어떻게 그런 일을 기억하지 못할 수 있겠는가?
Moreover, kernels are indeed crispy and fill the stomach,
게다가 알갱이가 정말 바삭바삭해서 배를 든든하게 채워주고,
quite delicious.
꽤 맛있어요.
But,
하지만,
it's been days now,
며칠이 지났는데,
and Tong Pass
그리고 통패스
hasn't sent a single letter.
편지 한 통도 보내지 않았습니다.
Are you worried about a certain someone
당신은 특정 사람에 대해 걱정하고 있습니까?
or Tong Pass?
아니면 통패스?
Lieutenant He,
그 중위,
I'm talking about serious matters.
나는 심각한 문제에 대해 이야기하고 있습니다.
Perhaps something has happened in the capital.
아마도 수도에서 무슨 일이 일어났을 수도 있습니다 .
So he might not have the time to write letters.
그래서 그 사람은 편지를 쓸 시간이 없을 수도 있어요 .
Lieutenant He,
그 중위,
who are you talking about?
누구 말하는 거야?
Who is he?
그는 누구입니까?
Even dried nuts
말린 견과류에도
can't stop you from talking.
당신이 말하는 것을 막을 수는 없습니다.
All right, I'll stop.
알았어, 그만할게.
But who is he?
그런데 그는 누구입니까?
Shiqi, an urgent report from Luoyang.
낙양에서 긴급 보고를 받은 시치.
Lord Linzi and Lord Kuaiji
Linzi 경과 Kuaiji 경
have already decided to withdraw their troops from Luoyang.
이미 뤄양에서 군대를 철수하기로 결정했습니다 .
(No movement from the enemy.)
(적의 움직임은 없습니다.)
My two brothers have always been filial
내 두 형제는 늘 효도했어요
(Provisions are being transported) since they were young.
(식량을 운반하고 있습니다) 어렸을 때부터.
It's no wonder
당연하지
my father has always cherished them.
아버지는 항상 그들을 소중히 여기셨습니다.
Luoyang was originally an advantage
낙양은 원래 유리했다
they took from you.
그들은 당신에게서 빼앗았습니다.
They naturally won't feel the pinch.
그들은 자연스럽게 꼬집음을 느끼지 않을 것입니다.
But now,
그러나 지금,
we're in a difficult situation.
우리는 어려운 상황에 처해 있습니다.
We absolutely cannot let go of Tong Pass.
우리는 통패스를 절대로 놓을 수 없습니다.
If Luoyang falls,
낙양이 무너지면
our army will be cut off.
우리 군대는 끊어질 것이다.
But Sun Jing
하지만 쑨징
is truly ruthless.
정말 무자비합니다.
If we don't withdraw the troops,
병력을 철수하지 않으면
he might really harm Lord Liang.
그는 Liang 경에게 정말로 해를 끼칠 수도 있습니다.
Shiqi, what do we do?
시치, 우리 어떡하지?
Shiqi!
시치!
From the emperor to the common people,
황제부터 일반 백성까지,
we all believe in the importance of being filial.
우리 모두는 효도의 중요성을 믿습니다 .
If we don't withdraw the troops,
병력을 철수하지 않으면
Sun Jing might really kill Lord Liang.
Sun Jing은 실제로 Liang 경을 죽일 수도 있습니다.
When that happens,
그런 일이 일어날 때,
there will be an uproar.
소란이 일어날 것입니다.
Those senior officials and army loyalists
그 고위 관료들과 군대에 충성하는 사람들
will all turn against us.
모두 우리에게 등을 돌릴 것이다.
Shiqi,
시치,
what should we do now?
우리는 지금 무엇을해야합니까?
Miss, you can't go.
아가씨, 당신은 갈 수 없습니다.
If you go,
당신이 가면,
you'll be walking into a death trap.
당신은 죽음의 함정에 빠지게 될 것입니다.
Qiucui,
치우쿠이,
please don't stop me.
나를 막지 마십시오.
I've never been favored
난 한번도 호의를 받은 적이 없어
by my parents at home.
집에서 부모님이.
I almost lost my life in Bingzhou.
나는 Bingzhou에서 목숨을 잃을 뻔했습니다.
If it weren't for Li Ni saving me,
리니가 나를 구해주지 않았다면
I might have become
내가 됐을지도 몰라
a mound of earth by now.
지금쯤이면 흙더미가 되어 있을 거에요.
When he saved me,
그가 나를 구했을 때,
he seemed like a god descending from heaven.
그는 마치 하늘에서 내려온 신 같았습니다 .
At that moment, I thought,
그 순간 나는 이렇게 생각했다.
perhaps he was the one I'd been waiting for.
어쩌면 그 사람이 바로 내가 기다리고 있던 사람이었을지도 모른다.
To repay him,
그에게 보답하기 위해,
I'm willing to give everything, even my life.
나는 모든 것, 심지어 내 목숨까지도 기꺼이 바칠 준비가 되어 있습니다.
But Miss,
그런데 아가씨,
you've had a tough life from a young age.
당신은 어려서부터 힘든 삶을 살았습니다 .
If you really lose your life because of this,
정말 이것 때문에 목숨을 잃는다면 ,
I'm afraid there won't be anyone left who truly cares about you.
진심으로 당신을 걱정해 주는 사람이 아무도 남지 않을 까봐 두렵습니다 .
Miss,
놓치다,
I want to go with you and make it back to Xichang alive.
나는 당신과 함께 가서 살아서 시창으로 돌아가고 싶습니다 .
Li Ni captured Luoyang
리니(Li Ni)가 낙양(洛陽)을 함락시켰다.
and Tong Pass after.
그리고 통 패스.
He advanced like the raging wind,
그는 성난 바람처럼 전진했고,
showing he was not an ordinary man.
그는 평범한 사람이 아니라는 것을 보여주었습니다.
He'll have a bright future.
그에게는 밝은 미래가 있을 것이다.
He's a person who values loyalty and righteousness.
그는 충성과 정의를 중시하는 사람이다 .
If I help him in times of danger,
내가 위험할 때 그를 도와주면
he'll surely remember
그 사람은 분명 기억할 거야
and repay me with gratitude.
그리고 감사한 마음으로 나에게 보답하세요.
If I can help him now,
지금 내가 그를 도울 수 있다면,
do I have to worry
내가 걱정해야 하나?
about having no place here?
여기에 자리가 없다고요?
If I don't strive now, when should I?
지금 노력하지 않으면 언제 해야 합니까?
Miss,
놓치다,
why do you suddenly
갑자기 왜 그래?
seem like a different person?
다른 사람 같은데?
Before, you never sought to compete or vie for anything.
이전에는 어떤 것에도 경쟁하거나 경쟁하려고 하지 않았습니다 .
Sometimes, when servants were disrespectful to you,
때로는 하인들이 당신에게 무례할 때도 있었습니다.
you wouldn't allow me to stand up for you.
당신은 내가 당신을 옹호하는 것을 허락하지 않을 것입니다 .
Qiucui,
치우쿠이,
I didn't strive
나는 노력하지 않았다
because I didn't have the strength
힘이 없었으니까
or the opportunity to compete.
또는 경쟁할 수 있는 기회.
So why bother if it's in vain?
그렇다면 그것이 헛된 일이라면 왜 귀찮게 합니까?
In the future,
미래에,
you'll be my trusted confidant.
당신은 나의 믿을만한 친구가 될 것입니다.
You must also learn
당신도 배워야 한다
to assess situations
상황을 평가하기 위해
and choose when to act wisely.
그리고 언제 현명하게 행동할지 선택하세요.
That's what smart people do.
그게 똑똑한 사람들이 하는 일이에요.
Greetings, General.
안녕하세요, 장군님.
Greetings, General Pei Yuan.
안녕하세요, 페이위안 장군님.
Miss Gu, no need to be formal.
구씨, 격식을 차릴 필요는 없어요.
I have a confidential matter
기밀 사항이 있습니다
to discuss with you.
당신과 논의하기 위해.
Miss Gu, please speak.
구씨, 말씀해주세요.
I heard Sun Jing
쑨징 들었어
uses Lord Liang to threaten you.
Lord Liang을 사용하여 당신을 위협합니다.
I'm willing to go to Xichang
나는 시창(Xichang)에 갈 의향이 있다
to act on your behalf
당신을 대신하여 행동하기 위해
and find a way to rescue Lord Liang.
그리고 리앙 경을 구출할 방법을 찾으세요.
Do you have any plans?
어떤 계획이라도 있나요?
In the capital, many influential and loyal families
수도에는 영향력 있고 충성스러운 가족이 많이 있습니다.
still support the country.
아직도 나라를 지지합니다.
However, Sun Jing is too powerful.
그러나 Sun Jing은 너무 강력합니다.
So they dare not speak out.
그래서 그들은 감히 말을 하지 못합니다.
Please provide a token to me.
나에게 토큰을 제공해주세요.
When I return to the capital,
수도로 돌아가면,
in your name,
당신의 이름으로,
I'll contact these noble families in secret,
나는 이 귀족 가문들에게 비밀리에 연락을 취하겠다.
and bribe the palace guards.
그리고 궁전 경비병들에게 뇌물을 주세요.
Perhaps, by using a strategic approach, we might be able to rescue Lord Liang.
어쩌면 전략적인 접근을 통해 양군을 구출할 수도 있을 것입니다.
No,
아니요,
it's too risky.
너무 위험해요.
If Sun Jing finds out,
Sun Jing이 알게 된다면,
or if someone betrays you,
아니면 누군가가 당신을 배신한다면,
it could cost you your life and implicate...
그것은 당신의 생명을 앗아갈 수 있고 연루될 수도 있습니다...
I'm not afraid of death.
나는 죽음을 두려워하지 않습니다.
If I die for righteousness,
내가 정의를 위해 죽는다면,
it would be an honorable death.
명예로운 죽음이 될 것입니다.
Even my father,
심지어 아버지도,
I'm sure you know
나는 당신이 알고 있다고 확신합니다
that he won't yield to that traitor, Sun Jing.
배신자 Sun Jing에게 굴복하지 않을 것입니다 .
He will surely agree with my decision.
그 사람도 분명 내 결정에 동의할 거예요.
Thank you for your loyalty, Miss Gu.
구 선생님의 충성심에 감사드립니다.
I've already made an arrangement in the capital.
나는 이미 수도에서 약속을 잡았습니다.
So you can rest assured.
그러니 안심하셔도 됩니다.
Jin'niang,
진냥,
did you say this letter
이 편지를 말했어?
was placed on the table,
테이블 위에 놓여 있었고,
but you don't know who delivered it?
그런데 누가 배달했는지 모르시나요?
Your Highness,
전하,
could it be a trap set by Grand Governor?
총독님이 쳐놓은 함정이 아닐까요 ?
No, it doesn't look like it.
아니요, 그렇지 않은 것 같습니다.
This letter is full of cryptic words.
이 편지는 비밀스러운 단어들로 가득 차 있습니다.
This letter is full of cryptic messages.
이 편지는 비밀스러운 메시지로 가득 차 있습니다.
But I understand
하지만 이해한다
what he's asking for.
그가 요구하는 것.
I think
제 생각에는
Li Ni wants to join forces with me.
Li Ni는 나와 힘을 합치고 싶어합니다.
He must have been planning this for a long time
그 사람은 이 일을 오랫동안 계획하고 있었나 봐
and finally had the confidence to rescue Lord Liang.
마침내 양경을 구출할 자신감을 갖게 되었습니다.
Your Highness, do we...
폐하, 우리는...
Of course, we'll help him.
물론, 우리는 그를 도울 것입니다.
Do as what was written in the letter.
편지에 적힌대로 하세요.
Move the orchid under the window.
난초를 창문 아래로 옮깁니다.
Yes, Your Highness.
예, 전하.
This is great, Miss.
정말 좋아요, 아가씨.
You don't need to take risks by going to Xichang anymore.
더 이상 시창에 가서 위험을 감수할 필요가 없습니다 .
His Highness will surely have a way to rescue Lord Liang.
전하께서는 반드시 양 공을 구출할 방법을 갖고 계실 것입니다.
Although he hasn't explicitly revealed the plan to me,
비록 그가 나에게 그 계획을 명시적으로 밝히지는 않았지만 ,
through this incident,
이번 사건을 통해
I have become someone he trusts.
나는 그가 신뢰하는 사람이 되었습니다.
Miss, are you planning...
아가씨, 계획 중이신가요...
Li Ni and Lieutenant He of the Cui Army
추이군의 리니와 허 중위
often have close contacts.
긴밀한 접촉을 하는 경우가 많습니다.
They seem to share a romantic connection.
그들은 낭만적인 관계를 공유하는 것 같습니다.
It's a good thing the Cui Army has returned to Yingzhou.
최군이 영주 로 돌아온 것은 좋은 일이다 .
So they'll be far apart.
그래서 그들은 멀리 떨어져 있을 것입니다.
If I'm someone he trusts,
내가 그 사람이 신뢰하는 사람이라면,
I'll naturally find a way
자연스럽게 방법을 찾게 될 거에요
to create some distance between him and Lieutenant He.
그와 He 중위 사이에 약간의 거리를 만들기 위해 .
If you could marry His Highness,
만약 당신이 전하와 결혼할 수 있다면,
it would be great.
그것은 좋은 것입니다.
Then, no one in the mansion would dare to look down on you.
그러면 저택의 어느 누구도 감히 당신을 무시하지 못할 것입니다.
But it's too early to talk about this now.
하지만 지금 이것에 대해 이야기하기에는 너무 이르다 .
I wonder if His Highness will be able
전하가 할 수 있을지 궁금해요
to rescue Lord Liang this time.
이번에는 양 경을 구출하기 위해.
To be honest,
솔직히 말하자면,
whether or not Lord Liang can be rescued
양경을 구출할 수 있을지 없을지
is entirely beneficial
전적으로 유익하다
for Li Ni.
리니를 위해.
Miss,
놓치다,
I don't understand.
모르겠어요.
If he successfully rescues Lord Liang,
만일 그가 양공을 구출하는데 성공한다면,
it would naturally be great.
당연히 좋을 것입니다.
After that, Li Ni would have unrestricted military power.
그 후 Li Ni는 무제한적인 군사력을 갖게 됩니다 .
If he failed to rescue Lord Liang,
만일 그가 양공(梁君)을 구출하는데 실패했다면,
and Lord Liang was killed by Sun Jing.
그리고 Liang 경은 Sun Jing에 의해 살해되었습니다.
Even in his grief,
그의 슬픔 속에서도
he won't need to fear consequences.
그는 결과를 두려워할 필요가 없을 것입니다.
Even if there is public criticism,
대중의 비난이 있어도
as long as Li Ni holds military authority,
리니가 군사적 권위를 갖고 있는 한 ,
who will dare to blame Li Ni in the future?
앞으로 누가 감히 Li Ni를 비난할 것인가 ?
Since Li Ni likes intelligent people,
리니는 똑똑한 사람을 좋아하기 때문에
I don't need to hide my cleverness
내 똑똑함을 숨길 필요는 없어
in front of him.
그 앞에서.
Do you think
당신은 생각합니까?
Li Ni will withdraw from Tong Pass
Li Ni가 Tong Pass에서 탈퇴합니다
like his brothers?
그의 형제들처럼?
What do you think?
어떻게 생각하나요?
If a battle is lost,
전투에서 패한 경우,
they can make a comeback.
그들은 돌아올 수 있습니다.
But once people's trust is lost,
하지만 일단 사람들의 신뢰를 잃으면
it's hard to get it back.
다시 돌려받기가 어렵습니다.
His brothers
그의 형제들
are already leaving Luoyang.
벌써 뤄양을 떠나고 있어요.
If Li Ni doesn't move,
리니가 움직이지 않으면
he'll be the subject of criticism.
비난의 대상이 될 것입니다.
I think he'll withdraw.
내 생각엔 그가 물러날 것 같아요.
Li Ni is a clever schemer.
Li Ni는 영리한 계획가입니다.
He likely already has a plan to rescue Lord Liang.
그는 이미 Liang 경을 구출할 계획을 가지고 있을 것입니다 .
Sun Jing is vigilant in guarding Lord Liang.
Sun Jing은 Liang 경을 경계하는 데 경계를 늦추지 않습니다.
It won't be easy to rescue him.
그를 구출하는 것은 쉽지 않을 것이다.
So, he needs to think carefully and come up with a plan.
그러므로 신중하게 생각 하고 계획을 세워야 합니다 .
Plus, he needs favorable timing, location, and cooperation.
게다가 유리한 시기와 위치, 협력도 필요하다.
But I think Li Ni
하지만 내 생각엔 리니가
already has an arrangement
이미 약속이 있어
for everything.
모두를위한.
Favorable timing, location, and cooperation?
유리한 시기, 위치, 협력?
What is considered favorable timing,
위치, 협력은 무엇이라고 간주되나요?
Taozi,
타오지,
do you still remember
아직도 기억해?
the medicine you formulated for him?
당신이 그 사람을 위해 만든 약은요?
Lieutenant He!
그 중위!
Lieutenant He,
그 중위,
urgent report from Yingzhou.
잉저우(Yingzhou)에서 긴급 보고를 받았습니다.
Young Master asked you to return to discuss this matter.
젊은 스승님께서 이 문제를 논의하기 위해 다시 오라고 하셨습니다 .
♪If I forget the fleeting of time♪
♪덧없는 시간을 잊어버린다면♪
♪Waiting for memories♪
♪추억을 기다리며♪
♪To shatter and sink♪
♪부서지고 가라앉도록♪
♪The emotional scars in your heart♪
♪마음 속 감정의 상처♪
♪Are the entanglement♪
♪얽혀 있군요♪
♪I find hard to let go of♪
♪놓기가 힘들어요♪
♪If longing is not forgotten♪
♪그리움이 잊혀지지 않는다면♪
♪I long to return to the very first moment♪
♪나는 처음의 순간으로 돌아가고 싶다 ♪
♪The affection we had in our fateful situation♪
♪ 운명적인 상황 속에서도 우리가 가졌던 애정 ♪
♪How I wish to keep it for you♪
♪당신을 위해 그것을 간직하고 싶습니다♪
♪If love still remembers♪
♪사랑이 아직도 기억한다면♪
♪The promises we made♪
♪우리가 한 약속♪
♪Even if this love hurts me♪
♪이 사랑이 나를 아프게 해도♪
♪I'll continue living for you♪
♪나는 계속 당신을 위해 살아갈게요♪
♪Holding onto the memories♪
♪추억을 붙잡고♪
♪Waiting is my persistence♪
♪기다림은 나의 끈기♪
♪If love remembers♪
♪사랑이 기억한다면♪
♪The promise I made to you♪
♪너와 한 약속♪
♪Despite going against fate♪
♪운명에도 불구하고♪
♪I have no regrets loving you♪
♪당신을 사랑한 걸 후회하지 않아요♪
♪I'm willing to sacrifice for you♪
♪당신을 위해 기꺼이 희생하겠습니다♪
♪As I wait for your answer♪
♪당신의 대답을 기다리면서♪
♪If love remembers♪
♪사랑이 기억한다면♪
♪The promise I made to you♪
♪너와 한 약속♪
♪Despite going against fate♪
♪운명에도 불구하고♪
♪I have no regrets loving you♪
♪당신을 사랑한 걸 후회하지 않아요♪
♪I'm willing to sacrifice for you♪
♪당신을 위해 기꺼이 희생하겠습니다♪
♪As I wait for your answer♪
♪당신의 대답을 기다리면서♪